A Guide to the Additional Papers of Dumas Malone 1913-1986
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Dumas Malone 1913-1986
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12712-b
This collection consists of ca. 25,300 items (66 Hollinger boxes, ca. 35 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The papers are unrestricted except for Box 26, which contains recommendations written by Dumas Malone on behalf of students and colleagues.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on March 18, 1987, by Mrs. Dumas Malone of Charlottesville, Virginia, through the agency of Mr. Gifford Malone of McLean, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the professional papers of Dumas Malone (1892-1986) consists of ca. 25,300 items (66 Hollinger boxes, ca. 35 linear feet), 1913-1986, chiefly concerning his work as a professor of history, editor of the Dictionary of American Biography, and biographer (of Thomas Jefferson) in residence at the University of Virginia.
Topical files and research and related materials for Jefferson and His Time form the bulk of the collection. Correspondence files were kept by Malone as part of his topical series, and can be found alphabetically under broad headings such as "personal correspondence," "miscellaneous correspondence," "professional correspondence," and "student correspondence."
Prominent correspondents in the topical files, listed with the folder heading in which they appear, include; John Lloyd Newcomb and Nicholas Murray Butler (Alderman Biography); Samuel Eliot Morison (American Historical Association); Allan Nevins (Columbia University); Justice Lewis F. Powell, Jr. (Correspondence re Thomas Jefferson); Carl Van Doren, Arthur Hays Sulzberger, Allan Nevins, Arthur Schlesinger, Allen Johnson, J. Franklin Jameson, and Charles Scribner ( Dictionary of American Biography); Daniel Boorstin, George Billias, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., John Chancellor, Francis P. Miller, A. Willis Robertson, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and Harry S. Truman (Names and Addresses); Robert Penn Warren (National Endowment for the Humanities); Justice Felix Frankfurter, Charles S. Robb, Warren Chappell, Charles F. Baldwin, Justice Lewis F. Powell, Jr., John H. Finley, Linwood Holton, President Jimmy Carter, and Mills E. Godwin, Jr. (Personal Correspondence); and George Bush and Admiral Hyman George Rickover (Presidental Medal of Freedom).
Other notables include: John F. Kennedy, Justice Felix Frankfurter, Nathaniel W. Stephanson, Allen Johnson, George McGovern, Julian P. Boyd, Allan Nevins, C. Vann Woodward, Harry Ammon, Max Lerner, Daniel Boorstin, Louis S. Auchincloss, Fawn Brodie, George F. Will, J. Harry Michael, Jr., Barbara Tuchman, and Walker Cowen (Professional Correspondence); Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Hardy C. Dillard, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and Linwood Holton (Pulitzer Prize) and Colgate Darden, Jr. (University of Virginia).
Also present are history book reviews, speeches, and articles by Malone; interviews with Malone (two on video cassette recordings); research files, research notecards, cassette tape recordings (148 tapes), and miscellaneous materials generated by Malone while writing his six-volume biography of Thomas Jefferson.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Individual files are generally in reverse chronological order and Mr. Malone's orginal order has been preserved whenever possible.
Organization
This collection is arranged in seven series: I. Topical Files (boxes 1-34); II. Miscellaneous Articles, Interviews, Reviews, and Speeches (boxes 35-41); III. Research Files for Jefferson and His Time(boxes 42-58); IV. Miscellaneous Materials re Jefferson and His Time(boxes 59-63); V. Video & Cassette Recordings, and Microfilm (boxes 64-66); VI. Research Notecards and VII. Oversize.
Contents List
- Topical Files
  - Alderman, Edwin A.-- Biography of 1931-1940 (Box 1)
  - American Historical Association -- Executive Committee 1936 (Box 1)
  - American Antiquarian Society, including "Mr. Jefferson's Private Life" 1974-1977 (Box 1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies Grant 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Americana Encyclopedia--Revised Article re Thomas Jefferson 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Appleton-Century-Crofts 1960-1073 (Box 1)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies 1972-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Associates of the University of Virginia Library Dinner 1981 (Box 1)
  - Awards--Miscellaneous 1935-1968 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Related Speeches 1982 (Box 2)
  - Bibliography of Malone Publications 1981 (Box 2)
  - Biographical Data on Dumas Malone 1926-1981 (Box 2)
  - Book Orders 1968-1977 (Box 2)
  - "Brief Biography of Thomas Jefferson" n.d., 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Brodie, Fawn McKay 1974-1981 (Box 3)
  - Brodie, Fawn-- Reviews of Thomas Jefferson: An Intimate History 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institution 1972-1976 (Box 3)
  - Bruce Catton Prize 1984 (Box 3)
  - CBS--Bicentenniel Program July 4, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Checklist of Dumas Malone's Writing 1967 (Box 3)
  - Class of 1910 1955 (Box 3)
  - Claude, Inis, Jr. 1975 (Box 3)
  - Clippings 1927-1986 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and Quotations 1943-1970 (Box 3)
  - Columbia University--Correspondence re 1945 & 1955-1959 (Box 4)
  - Coolidge, Ellen Randolph Letter in the American Antiquarian Society Proceedings 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Copeley Hill Project 1952-1959 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence re Thomas Jefferson 1974-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Dabney, Virginius-- The Jefferson Scandals: A Rebuttal 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Clippings 1931-1946 (Box 4)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Correspondence 1975-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Correspondence 1926-1974, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Memoir of Adolph Simon Ochs (1858-1935) 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Minutes of the Committee of Management 1925-1933, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Report 1936 (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Statistics n.d. (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Story of the Enterprise 1936 (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Vol. XX n.d. (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of American Biography--Revised Article on Thomas Jefferson for Thomas Jefferson: A Reference Biography1984 (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of Literary Biography--Article re Dumas Malone 1978-1983 (Box 6)
  - Dinner Party Commemorating the Completion of Jefferson and His Time given by the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation and UVA 1981 (Box 6)
  - Dissertations directed by Malone at Columbia University 1956-1959 (Box 7)
  - Dissertations (Remote) 1951-1957 (Box 7)
  - Education School of the University of Virginia Conference November 14, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Emory University 1980-1982 (Box 7)
  - "The Estate"--A Play about Thomas Jefferson 1976 (Box 7)
  - "Eye of Thomas Jefferson"-- Exhibit at the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. 1974-1976 (Box 7)
  - Examinations for History Classes 1950-1958 (Box 7)
  - Fan Letters 1982-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Fan Letters 1970, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Founder's Day at the University of Virginia 1976 (Box 8)
  - Freak Letters 1948-1986 (Box 7)
  - Freeman, Douglas Southall ca. 1954 (Box 8)
  - Graphics Communications Services 1976 (Box 8)
  - Greece, Ancient--Notes n.d. (Box 8)
  - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation 1950-1960, & 1985 (Box 8)
  - Hampden-Sydney College Honorary Degree 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - Harvard University Press 1938-1942 (Box 8)
  - Harvard University Press History 1982 (Box 9)
  - Hemings, Sally--Controversy 1971-1979 (Box 9)
  - History Book Club 1969-1984, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Hochman, Steve--Clippings re 1981 (Box 10)
  - Holton, Gov. Linwood-- Reception and Dinner for Distinguished Virginians 1972 (Box 10)
  - Jefferson Bible 1974-1977 (Box 10)
  - The Jeffersonian Heritage-- Correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 10)
  - "Journey With Jefferson" 1982 (Box 10)
  - Judiciary - Ranking of Supreme Court Justices 1974 (Box 10)
  - Knudson, Jerry 1874-1976 (Box 10)
    re Fawn Bodie reviews
  - Library of Congress--Consultant in American History 1968-1970 (Box 10)
  - Library of Congress--Dedication Ceremony 1976 (Box 10)
  - Literary Society of Washington, D.C. 1932-1935 & 1978-1980, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Little, Brown, and Company 1975-1984, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Little, Brown, and Company 1938-1974, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - Little, Brown, and Company --Library of American Biography Series 1981-1984 (Box 11)
  - Louisana Purchase Proclamation 1971-1974 (Box 12)
  - Madison Papers Annual Reports 1957 & 1970-1985 (Box 12)
  - Malone, Kemp--Clippings 1966-1977 (Box 12)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society -- Kennedy Medal 1971-1977 (Box 12)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company 1974 (Box 12)
  - Memorabilia 1945-1983, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous 1922-1983 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1968-1982, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Missouri Historical Society 1975-1977 (Box 13)
  - Monticello Association Meetings 1975-1983, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - "Morris Plan Bank Letter" (Thomas Jefferson to Craven Peyton, November 27, 1803) 1978 June (Box 13)
  - Muth, Dayis of the Christian Science Center 1981-1983 (Box 13)
  - Names and Addresses -- A-W 1956-1966, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - National Archives 1971-1974 (Box 14)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities 1974-1982 (Box 14)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities--Celebration of its 15th Anniversary at the White House 1980 (Box 14)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants 1967-1975, 6 folders (Box 15)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants -- Applications 1971-1981 (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants -- Budgets 1972-1981 (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants -- Interim Expenditures Reports and/or Cash Requests 1972-1981 (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grants-- Miscellaneous Financial Records 1972-1981, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Jefferson Lecture Series 1971-1973 (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Testimonial for Dumas Malone at the Rotunda 1979 (Box 17)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities White House Luncheon 1981 (Box 17)
  - National Foundation on the Arts and the Humanities 1965-1967 (Box 17)
  - National Geographic Society Article 1974 (Box 17)
    re Thomas Jefferson
  - National Historical Society Assembly 1970-1971 (Box 17)
  - National Potrait Galley-- Symposium on the Art of Biography 1978 (Box 17)
  - New Orleans Pulitzer Prize Acceptance 1976 (Box 17)
  - Olsen, David (Jefferson Film) 1974-1977 (Box 17)
  - Oxford University Press -- The Story of the Declaration of Independence 1945-1959 & 1972-1979, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Papers of Thomas Jefferson (Princeton)--Correspondence 1946-1950 (Box 17)
  - Patrick Henry Memorial Foundation 1984 (Box 18)
  - Personal Correspondence 1947-1982, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - Personnel--Steve Hochman 1968-1971 (Box 18)
  - Personnel - Dumas Malone 1968-1971 (Box 18)
  - Personnel -- Kay Sargeant 1968-1970 (Box 18)
  - Phi Beta Kappa--Visiting Scholars Program 1963-1968 (Box 19)
  - Phi Beta Kappa--Visiting Scholars Program Visits by Dumas Malone 1964-1967, 8 folders (Box 19)
  - Photographs of Dumas Malone ca. 1968-1981 (Box 20)
  - Photograph 1976 & n.d. (Box 20)
  - Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell --Memoir re 1934 (Box 20)
  - Poplar Forest 1984 (Box 20)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc. 1973-1984 (Box 20)
  - Presidential Medal of Freedom 1983 (Box 20)
  - Princeton University Press 1975-1976 (Box 20)
  - Printing Office--University of Virginia 1967-1976 (Box 20)
  - Professional Correspondence 1986 Jan- 1987 Mar, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Professional Correspondence 1979-1985, 6 folders (Box 21)
  - Professional Correspondence 1975 Aug- 1978, 6 folders (Box 22)
  - Professional Correspondence 1971-1975 Jul, 6 folders (Box 23)
  - Professional Correspondence 1923-1970, 6 folders (Box 24)
  - Progress Report of the Biographer-in-Residence 1963-1970 (Box 24)
  - Projects- Future 1974-1979 (Box 24)
  - Pulitzer Prize Congratulations 1975, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Pulitzer Prize Clipping 1975 (Box 25)
  - Queen Elizabeth II of Great Britain's Visit to Charlottesville (July 10, 1976) 1976-1977 (Box 25)
  - Radio Program "Virginia and the American Revolution" --WRFK, Richmond 1975-1976 (Box 25)
  - Reading List for History Classes 1947-1962 (Box 25)
  - Recommendations 1963-1985, 8 folders (Box 26)
  - Recording for the Blind 1977-1981 (Box 27)
  - Reprints of Articles, Permission for 1972-1980 (Box 27)
  - Requests--General 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Reviews of The Public Life of Thomas Cooper 1783-1829 by Dumas Malone 1926-1927 (Box 27)
  - Rockefeller Foundation 1943-1950 & 1984 (Box 27)
  - "Sally Hemings"--Television Mini-series 1979-1980 (Box 27)
  - Sigma Nu Fraternity 1979-1980 (Box 27)
  - Smithsonian Institution & Magazine 1975-1978 & 1981 (Box 27)
  - Society of Fellows, University of Virginia 1968-1973 (Box 27)
  - Southern Historical Association 1967-1977 (Box 28)
  - Southern Historical Association Dinner in Atlanta 1967 (Box 28)
  - Speaking Engagements and Projects 1968-1969 (Box 28)
  - Student Correspondence 1950-1984, 3 folders (Box 28)
  - Swarthmore College Examination 1935-1936 (Box 28)
  - Television Series 1981-1982 (Box 28)
  - Term Papers about Dumas Malone 1976, 1984, & n.d. (Box 29)
  - Textbook ( Empire for Liberty) --Comments re 1955-1958, 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Textbook ( Empire for Liberty)--Correspondence re 1947-1960, 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Textbook ( Empire for Liberty) -- Maps & Charts 1955-1957 (Box 29)
  - Textbook ( Empire for Liberty) --Reviews 1960 (Box 29)
  - Thomas Jefferson Award--Dumas Malone 1964 (Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson Award-- Nominations 1976 & 1981 (Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1970-1985, 7 folders (Box 30)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1957-1969, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation--Board of Directors 1955-1960 (Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation--Dinner Menus and Guest Lists 1960-1982 (Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation--Expense Account 1960-1965 (Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation--Trust Fund 1959-1965 (Box 31)
  - Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia --Honorary Degree of Doctor of Laws 1982-1983 (Box 31)
  - Thomasson-Grant Book on Monticello 1983 (Box 31)
  - Travel Diary of Trip to Italy 1959 (Box 31)
  - Trips (Lectures Given by Malone) 1950-1968, 7 folders (Box 32)
  - University of Virginia 1974-1983, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - University of Virginia 1948-1973, 3 folders (Box 33)
  - University of Virginia - Dedication of Alderman Library 1938 (Box 33)
  - University of Viriginia - History Department 1972-1983 (Box 33)
  - University of Virginia -- "Jefferson in Perspective" Continuing Education Course 1973 (Box 33)
  - Vidal, Gore -- Burr: A Novel1974 (Box 33)
  - Villa Serbelloni 1970-1973 (Box 33)
  - Virginia Cultural Laureate Society 1985-1986 (Box 34)
  - Virginia Cultural Laureate Center 1981-1982 (Box 34)
  - Virginia Forum on Education 1980 (Box 34)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute--Departmental Visiting Scholar 1967-1968 (Box 34)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute --Visit 1976 (Box 34)
  - Virginia State Library 1981-1982 (Box 34)
  - Virginia's Writer's Club 1981-1982 (Box 34)
  - Visualtek-Miniviewer Electronic Visual Aid 1977-1981 (Box 34)
  - Voice of America Program 1976 (Box 34)
  - Wall Street Journal Letter to the Editor 1975 Dec-1976 May (Box 34)
  - Washington, George --Articles re 1953-1960 & n.d. (Box 34)
  - Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri 1975-1976 (Box 34)
  - Weymouth, Lally--Book on Thomas Jefferson 1972-1974 (Box 34)
  - White, Goodrich C. --Correspondence 1944-1945 (Box 34)
  - William & Mary College Honorary Degree 1976-1981 (Box 34)
  - Williamsburg Anniversary--Virginia Resolution for Independence 1976 (Box 34)
  - World Publishing Company 1960-1971 (Box 34)
  - Yale--Wilbur Lucius Cross Medal 1972 (Box 34)
  - Yorktown Bicentennial 1981 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous Articles, Interviews, Reviews, and Speeches
  - Articles in The New York Times by Malone 1950-1960 (Box 35)
  - Articles in Virginia Quarterly Review by Malone 1928-1975 (Box 35)
  - Articles, Miscellaneous by Dumas Malone 1923-1975 & n.d., 3 folders (Box 35)
  - "Geography of American Acheivement" and related material by Dumas Malone 1924-1940 (Box 36)
  - "Thomas Jefferson and the Library of Congress" and related material by Malone 1976-1977 (Box 36)
  - Articles 1948 & 1970-1981, 4 folders (Box 36)
    re Dumas Malone
  - Miscellaneous Early Writings of Dumas Malone ca. 1913-1922 (Box 36)
  - Interviews with Dumas Malone and Related Material 1954-1982, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - University of Virginia Manuscript Department Exhibition Honoring Dumas Malone and Interview 1981 (Box 37)
  - "Today Show" Interview on NBC 1976 (Box 37)
  - United States Information Agency Interview of Dumas Malone 1982-1984 (Box 37)
  - Reviews by Dumas Malone for the History Book Club 1953-1966, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Reviews, Miscellaneous by Dumas Malone 1929-1965, & n.d., 4 folders (Box 38)
  - Reviews of Books About Southern History by Dumas Malone 1948-1951 (Box 38)
  - Reviews 1976 (Box 38)
    re The Story of the Declaration of Independence(Oxford University Press)
  - Reviews 1963-1964 (Box 38)
    re Thomas Jefferson as Political Leader
  - Speeches by Dumas Malone 1952-1986, 7 folders (Box 39)
  - Speeches by Dumas Malone 1939-1958, 7 folders (Box 40)
  - Speeches by Dumas Malone 1932-1938, n.d., 7 folders (Box 41)
  - Speeches -- Correspondence re 1947-1963 (Box 41)
  - Speeches - List of n.d. (Box 41)
- Research Files for Jefferson and His Time
  - General
    - Adams, John (1735-1826) n.d. (Box 42)
    - Adams, John n.d. (Box 42)
      Statements, Actions & Beliefs re Political Matters
    - Adams, John Quincy n.d. (Box 42)
    - Batture Case n.d., 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Bollman, Erick n.d. (Box 42)
    - Burr, Aaron & the Burr Conspiracy n.d., 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Burr Conspiracy & Related Materials n.d., 10 folders (Box 43)
    - Calenders n.d. (Box 44)
    - Callender, James T. n.d., 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Carr Family n.d. (Box 44)
    - Chronology (Tentative) n.d. (Box 44)
    - Church, Angelica 1970 (Box 44)
    - Civil Liberties and Libel Cases 1963-1970, n.d., 3 folders (Box 44)
    - Clark, William n.d. (Box 44)
    - Cooper, William-- Politics n.d. (Box 44)
    - Cooper, Thomas, Thomas Jefferson and the University of Virginia n.d., 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Domestic Affairs n.d., 3 folders (Box 45)
    - Duane, William n.d. (Box 45)
    - Embargo n.d., 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Embargo n.d., 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Eppes, Francis (1801-1881) n.d., 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Eppes, John Wayles and Poplar Forest n.d. (Box 46)
    - Family of Jefferson and Related Materials n.d., 4 folders (Box 46)
    - Foreign Affairs and Correspondence n.d., 5 folders (Box 47)
    - Gallatin, Albert n.d. (Box 47)
    - Giles, William Branch (1762-1830) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Gilmer, Francis Walker (1790-1826) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Hamilton, Alexander (1757-1804) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Hay, George, and Caesar A. Rodney n.d. (Box 47)
    - Hemings, Madison -- Narrative n.d. (Box 47)
    - Henry, Patrick n.d. (Box 47)
    - Humbolt, Baron Alexander von n.d. (Box 47)
    - Internal Improvements n.d. (Box 47)
    - Itinerary of Thomas Jefferson (1809-1826) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Jefferson, Martha (1772-1836) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Jefferson, Martha (1778-1804) n.d. (Box 47)
    - Jefferson, Thomas -- Biography n.d. (Box 48)
    - Jefferson, Thomas and James Madison n.d. (Box 48)
    - Kosciuszko, Thaddeus n.d. (Box 48)
    - Lefayette, Marquis de 1942-1979 (Box 48)
    - Letters & Memoranda, 1809-1826 n.d., 3 folders (Box 48)
    - Letters of the Dupont Family n.d. (Box 48)
    - Letters between Jefferson and Adams n.d. (Box 48)
    - Letters between Jefferson and Madison n.d. (Box 48)
    - Letters between Jefferson, and Monroe, Hamilton, Madison, and Gallatin n.d. (Box 48)
    - Letters of Thomas Jefferson Randolph n.d. (Box 48)
    - Lewis and Clark 1961-1969 & n.d. (Box 49)
    - Littlepage, Lewis 1956-1957 (Box 49)
    - Madison, Dolly 1957 (Box 49)
    - Madison, James 1945-1971 (Box 49)
    - Marshall, John (1775-1835) 1941-1942 (Box 49)
    - Marshall, John -- Life of George Washingtonn.d. (Box 49)
    - Mazzei, Philip (1730-1816) 1951-1980 (Box 49)
    - Military and Naval Affairs n.d., 2 folders (Box 49)
    - Monroe, James (1758-1831) 1947-1963 (Box 49)
    - Missouri Controversy n.d. (Box 49)
    - National Defense -- Contemporary Comments n.d. (Box 49)
    - Navy n.d. (Box 50)
    - Newspaper Notes n.d. (Box 50)
    - Paine, Thomas n.d. (Box 50)
    - Peale, Charles Wilson n.d. (Box 50)
    - Personal n.d. (Box 50)
    - Plumer, Senator William n.d. (Box 50)
    - Politics n.d. (Box 50)
    - Public n.d. (Box 50)
    - Randolph, Thomas Jefferson (1792-1875) 1955 & n.d. (Box 50)
    - Randolph, Thomas Mann (1768-1828) 1950-1971, & n.d. (Box 50)
    - Randolph, John n.d. (Box 50)
    - Rush, Benjamin (1745-1813) 1951 & n.d. (Box 50)
    - Short, William 1959-1971 (Box 51)
    - Slaves and Slavery 1967 & n.d., 3 folders (Box 51)
    - Taylor, John (1753-1824) 1944 & n.d. (Box 51)
    - Trumbull, John 1949-1950 (Box 51)
    - Truxton, Thomas n.d. (Box 51)
    - Volney, Comte de n.d. (Box 51)
    - Walker, John and the Walker Affairs n.d. (Box 51)
    - War of 1812 n.d. (Box 51)
    - Warden, David B. 1941 (Box 51)
    - Weather n.d. (Box 51)
    - Wilkinson, General James n.d., 2 folders (Box 52)
    - Wirt, William n.d. (Box 52)
    - Wythe, George (1726-1806) 1976 & n.d. (Box 52)
  - Thomas Jefferson
    - Agriculture n.d. (Box 52)
    - Albemarle County, Virginia n.d. (Box 52)
    - Animals: Dogs, Horse, etc. n.d. (Box 52)
    - Archaelogy n.d. (Box 52)
    - Architecture n.d. (Box 52)
    - Arts 1957-1978 (Box 52)
    - Books 1944-1976 (Box 52)
    - Classics 1943 & n.d. (Box 52)
    - Climate and Winds 1974 & n.d. (Box 52)
    - Costumes and Dress, etc. 1972 (Box 52)
    - Country vs. City--View of Jefferson 1975 (Box 53)
    - Constitution, First Amendment to 1972 (Box 53)
    - Cryptography 1971 (Box 53)
    - Descriptions of Jefferson 1963-1984, n.d. (Box 53)
    - Family Correspondence (Henry E. Huntington Library) 1941 & n.d. (Box 53)
    - Farmbook and Agriculture Operation n.d. (Box 53)
    - Friendship n.d. (Box 53)
    - Gardens and Grounds of Monticello 1967-1971 (Box 53)
    - Genealogy of the Jefferson Family 1960-1979 (Box 53)
    - Habits of Study n.d. (Box 53)
    - Health 1984 & n.d. (Box 53)
    - History, General 1955-1959 (Box 53)
    - History - Comments of the Revolutionary and Saxon Periods n.d. (Box 53)
    - Indians 1971 & n.d. (Box 53)
    - Interpretations of Jefferson 1956-1978, 2 folders (Box 54)
    - Italy--Jefferson's Travels 1946 & 1971 (Box 54)
    - Jefferson Materials from James Bear, Jr. 1957 (Box 54)
    - Jefferson Monument at the University of Missouri 1977 (Box 54)
    - Law Practices of Thomas Jefferson 1977 & 1984, 2 folders (Box 54)
    - Library of Thomas Jefferson n.d., 2 folders (Box 54)
    - Libraries, Later, and Reading of Jefferson 1944-1976 (Box 55)
    - Manuscripts of Thomas Jefferson at the University of Virginia 1957 & 1963 (Box 55)
    - Medicine 1975-1977 (Box 55)
    - Miscellaneous Quotes n.d. (Box 55)
    - Miscegenation--Sally Hemmings Issue n.d. (Box 55)
    - Monticello -- Articles re by James Bear, Jr. 1957-1972 (Box 55)
    - Monticello--Construction n.d. (Box 55)
    - Monticello -- Descriptions of 1973-1980, & n.d. (Box 55)